这里是博克岛
This is Berk,
是... 世界上最大的秘密
the best kept secret this side of, well... anywhere.
尽管看上去不怎么样
Granted, it may not look like much,
但由此湿润山石堆砌而成的博克岛绝对让你叹为观止
but this wet heap of rock packs more than a few surprises.
这里的生活超级棒 但是不太适合胆小的人
Life here is amazing, just not for the faint of heart.
你知道其他地方的人都喜欢木工和针线活
You see, where most folks enjoy hobbies like whittling or needlepoint,
而我们博克人更喜欢...
we Berkians prefer...
做点小运动 我们称之为...
a little something we like to call...
赛龙!
Dragon racing!
哇吼吼! 吼吼! 不好意思啊 鱼脚司 你想要这个?
Whoa-ho-ho! Ho-ho! I'm sorry, Fishlegs, did you want that?
哦 鼻涕虫 那是我的!
Oh, Snotlout, that was mine!
给你 宝贝
Here you go, babe.
我有没有说过你今天很美? 因为你真的很美
Did I tell you that you look amazing today? 'Cause you do.
呃! 快点走 吐吐 有臭气过来了
Ugh! Come on, Barf. It's starting to stink around here.
不 我还是很恨你 我们来扫平这片地吧 喷喷!
Nope, still hates you. Let's blow this place, Belch!
好吧!
All right!
哦 耶!
Oh, yeah!
啊 哈哈! 那是双胞胎的第九只了!
Ah, ha-ha! That's nine for the twins!
阿丝翠德只有三只!
Astrid lags with three!
鱼脚司和鼻涕虫一只都没有!
Fishlegs and Snotlout trail with none!
而小嗝嗝...
And Hiccup is...
不见人影 唔
Nowhere to be found. Hmm.
难道不是你说那么大的事儿把他吓跑的吗 斯多戈?
Scared him off with the big talk, didn't you, Stoick?
你在干嘛 鼻涕虫? 他们就要赢了
What are you doing, Snotlout? They're gonna win now.
她是我的公主... 她想要什么我都给她
She's my princess... whatever she wants, she gets.
拉芙纳特? 她之前不是要把你活埋了吗?
Ruffnut? Didn't she try to bury you alive?
只是一会儿啦
Only for a few hours.
龙曾经在这里是个麻烦
Now, dragons used to be a bit of a problem here,
但那已经是五年前的事了 现在都已经融入了我们
but that was five years ago. Now they've all moved in.
而且说实话 为什么不呢?
And, really, why wouldn't they?
我们有定做的龙棚 什么都能吃到的食槽
We have custom stables, all-you-can-eat feeding stations,
洗浴桑拿一条龙服务...
a full-service dragon wash...
甚至还有用绳子吊着的防火设施
even top-of-the-line fire prevention, if I do say so myself.
- 啊 时间到了 高博 - 准备好了 最后一圈!
- Ah, it's time, Gobber. - Righty-ho. Last lap!
黑羊! 快 暴飞飞! 我们还能靠这个赢!
The black sheep! Come on, Stormfly! We can still win this thing!
- 快点 吐吐! - 我们上!
- Come on, Barf! - Let's go!
快 肉丸儿!
Go, Meatlug!
快点 快点 快点!
Let's go, let's go, let's go!
这可是你的重要时刻 飞行愉快
This is your big moment. Have a nice flight.
上! 上 上 上 上 上!
Up! Up, up, up, up, up!
干得好 肉丸儿!
Good job, Meatlug!
给你 亲爱的 这个顶十只羊
Here you go, darling. Mine's worth ten.
耶! 黑羊到手!
Yeah! The black sheep!
你们是在争拉芙纳特吗?
You guys are fighting for Ruffnut?
- 我赢定了! - 我们一起赢
- I'm totally winning! - We're winning together.
哦 不!
Oh, no!
喔! 没人能阻止我啦!
Whoo! No one can stop me now!
除了我 我们可是连在一起的 小天才
Except for me. We're attached, genius.
- 少来抢我的荣誉! - 嘿!
- Quit trying to steal all my glory! - Hey!
抢他们的 阿丝翠德!
Get them, Astrid!
- 是我的荣誉! - 你老是弄砸一切!
- It's my glory! - Always ruining everything!
- 无羊不荣耀! - 拿到啦! 哈哈!
- No, sheep, no glory! - Gotcha! Ha-ha!
- 哇哦! - 阿丝翠德!
- Whoa! - Astrid!
干得好!
Well played!
那可是我未来儿媳妇!
That's my future daughter-in-law!
喔吼!
Whoo-hoo!
- 啊 不好意思了 - 暴飞飞!
- Uh, excuse me. - Stormfly!
哇哦!
Whoa!
十三只! 阿丝翠德赢了!
That's 13! Astrid takes the game!
没错 博克岛是个非常棒的地方
Yep, Berk is pretty much perfect.
我的所有努力都有了回报 这是件好事
All of my hard work has paid off. And it's a good thing, too,
因为我们维京人骑在龙背上...
because with Vikings on the backs of dragons...
世界变得更加广阔了
the world just got a whole lot bigger.
耶!
Yeah!
你觉得怎么样 伙计? 想要再来一次吗?
What do you think, bud? You want to give this another shot?
没牙仔! 不会有事的
Toothless! It'll be fine.
准备好了吗?
Ready?
耶...!
Yeah...!
耶!
Yeah!
哇哦!
Whoa!
耶!
Yeah!
这可太棒了!
This is amazing!
这可不怎么棒 没牙仔!
No longer amazing. Toothless!
哦 不!
Oh, no!
哇哦!
Whoa!
这真是突发事件啊
That really came out of nowhere.
我们真得处理一下你的单边尾翼了 伙计
We-we got to work on your solo gliding there, bud.
所以 呃 是因为尾巴被锁了所以营救不够及时 是吗?
That, uh, locked-up tail makes for some pretty sloppy rescue maneuvers, hey?
看来我们又发现一处美景 伙计
Looks like we found another one, bud.
哦 怎么 你想我道歉?
Oh, what, do you want an apology?
所以你又撅嘴撒娇啊?
Is that why you're pouting, big baby boo?
好吧 试试这个!
Well, try this on!
哦 你感受到了吗? 哈? 感受到我真心的悔恨了吗?
Oh, you feeling it yet? Huh? Picking up on all my heartfelt remorse?
啊 耶 哦 别这样 别这样 你不会伤害独腿...
Ah. Yeah. Oh, come on, come on, you-you wouldn't hurt a one-legged...
呃... 你 你说得对 你说得对 你赢了 你赢了
Uh... Y-you're right, you're right. You win. You win.
他被打倒了! 输得真惨啊! 龙和维京勇士...
He's down! And it's ugly! Dragons and Vikings...
又变成敌人了 苦战缠身...
enemies again. Locked in combat to the bitter...
哦...!
Oh...!
你知道这洗不掉
You know that doesn't wash out.
那么 我们给这地方起什么名字?
So, what should we name it?
那就"痒痒的胳肢窝"
"Itchy armpit" it is.
你在想什么 伙计? 在想我们可能在这里发现几个伐木工?
What do you reckon, bud? Think we might find a few Timberjacks in those woods?
还是说石头里有低语的死神?
The odd whispering death or two in the rocks?
谁知道呢 也许我们能找到另一个夜煞
Who knows, maybe we'll finally track down another Night Fury.
那也挺棒的
Wouldn't that be something.
那么 你有什么想法? 继续这样下去?
So, what do you say? Just keep going?
下午好 女士 你去哪儿了?
Afternoon, milady. Where have you been?
嗨
Hi.
哦 去赢比赛呗 还能有什么?
Oh, winning races. What else?
真正该问的是 你去哪儿了?
The real question is, where have you been?
- 躲我老爸 - 哦 不 这次是什么事儿?
- Avoiding my dad. - Oh, no. What happened now?
哦 你会... 你会喜欢这事儿的
Oh, you're gonna... You're gonna love this.
今天早上我起床 阳光明媚 恐怖龙在屋顶歌唱
I wake up, the sun's shining, terrible terrors are singing on the rooftop,
我悠闲地去吃早餐 想着这世界多美妙 然后他跟我说:
I saunter down to breakfast thinking all is right with the world, and I get:
"儿子 我们得谈一谈"
"Son, we need to talk."
"现在别 老爸 我还得开始今天的游手好闲呢"
"Not, now, Dad. I got a whole day of goofing off to get started."
好吧 首先 我的声音不是那样的 你模仿的那是谁啊?
Okay, first of all, I don't sound like that. What is this character?
还有... 还有其次...
And... and second...
你学我时那么抖肩膀是怎么回事?
What is that thing you're doing with my shoulders?
好吧 那还真是个讨喜的模仿
Yeah, that's a really flattering impersonation.
然后他接着说...
Anyway, he goes...
"你是博克岛的骄傲 儿子 我也感觉无比自豪"
"You're the pride of Berk, son, and I couldn't be prouder."
哦 谢谢 老爸 我也觉得自己很厉害
Aw, thanks, Dad. I'm pretty impressed with myself, too.
我的手什么时候那样比划过?
When have I ever done that with my hands?
- 你刚刚就是! - 好吧 现在...
- You just did! - Okay, just...
待着... 别动
Hold... still.
- 很严肃的 - 嗯哼
- Very serious. - Mm-hmm.
"你已经长大了
"You're all grown up,
因为首领找不到更好的继承人...
and since no chief could ask for a better successor...
- 我决定..." - 让你当首领!
- I've decided..." - To make you chief!
哦 我的天啊! 小嗝嗝 这太棒了!
Oh, my gods! Hiccup, that's amazing!
哦...!
Oh...!
你会打坏弹簧圈的 校准很麻烦的
You're gonna wear out the spring coil. The calibration is very sensitive.
好吧 那么...
Yeah, so...
就是这事儿
this is what I'm dealing with.
你怎么跟他说的?
What did you tell him?
我... 什么都没说 他转身的瞬间我就跑了
I... I didn't. By the time he turned around, I was gone.
哈 好吧... 这是个很重的担子
Huh. Well... it's a lot of responsibility.
地图要先放放了 这是肯定的
The map will have to wait, for sure,
而且... 我得去遛没牙仔 因为你会很忙 但是...
and... and I'll need to fly Toothless, since you'll be too busy, but...
那不是我 阿丝翠德 所有的演讲 计划 还有管理整个村子
it's not me, Astrid. All those speeches and planning and running the village,
- 那是他的事 - 我觉得你忘了重点
- that's his thing. - I think you're missing the point.
我是说... 首领啊 多么荣耀的事!
I mean... chief. What an honor!
如果是我的话 我会超级激动
I'd be pretty excited.
我... 我不是你
I... I'm not like you.
你... 你清楚地知道你是谁 你一直都知道 但是...
You... know exactly who you are, you always have, but...
我还在寻找 我知道我不是我父亲
I'm still looking. I know that I'm not my father,
我也从没见过我妈妈 所以... 我到底是谁?
and I never met my mother, so... What does that make me?
你寻找的东西并不在外面 小嗝嗝...
What you're searching for isn't out there, Hiccup...
它在这里
It's in here.
也许你只是还没发现而已
Maybe you just don't see it yet.
- 啊 啊! - 也许吧
- Ugh. Ugh! - Maybe.
但是 你知道的... 外面的确有些什么
But, you know... there is something out there.
小嗝嗝...
Hiccup...
哇哦...
Wow...
跟紧点
Stay close.
这里发生了什么?
What happened here?
好吧 放松 伙计
All right, e-easy, bud.
小嗝嗝!
Hiccup!
- 开火! - 阿丝翠德 小心!
- Fire! - Astrid, look out!
小嗝嗝!
Hiccup!
小心尾巴!
Watch the tail!
把腿绑住!
Tie those legs up!
我没有眼花吧?
Is that what I think it is?
- 住手! - 暴飞飞!
- Stop! - Stormfly!
你们在做什么?!
What are you doing?!
又回来了!
Back again!
吓尿了 那可是只夜煞
Soil my britches. That is a Night Fury.
我还以为它们永远的消失了呢
Thought they were all gone for good.
看来我们时来运转了 伙计们!
Looks like our luck's had a turn for the better, lads!
我想德雷格的龙族战队里... 可没有这么一只龙
Don't think Drago has one of those... in his dragon army.
龙族战队?
Dragon army?
听着 我们不想惹麻烦
Look, we don't want any trouble.
哈! 这种事你应该在偷了我们所有的龙
Hah! You should have thought of that before you stole all of our dragons
还把我们的碉堡炸成碎片之前就想好!
and blasted our fort to bits!
- 等等 - 你在说什么?
- Wait. - What are you talking about?
你觉得是我们干的?
You think we did this?
哈! 没有好的驯龙骑士从中协助
Hah! Dragon trapping is hard enough work as it is
捕龙者的工作已经很艰辛了
without do-gooder Dragon Riders sneaking in to rescue them.
什么好的...? 还有其他的驯龙骑士?
What do-gooder...? There are other Dragon Riders?
你是说除了你昨晚的小偷朋友以外吗?
You mean other than your thieving friend from last night?
你告诉我 你也许有一只会喷冰的龙
You tell me. You may have an ice-spitting dragon on your side,
但我们这边还差一只
but we still have a quota to fill.
你让我们怎么跟德雷格·布拉维斯特交代?
How do you suppose we explain this mess to Drago Bludvist?
德雷格什么玩意? 你知道你自己在说什么吗?
Drago what-fist? Does anything you say make sense?
他还等着在明天之前拿到一批新龙呢
He's expecting a new shipment of dragons for his army by tomorrow.
而且德雷格不听任何借口!
And Drago don't take well to excuses!
这是上次我空手去见他他给我留下的
This is what he gave me last time I showed up empty-handed.
在未来他只会变得更不近人情
He promised to be far less understanding in the future.
好吧 听着 我根本不知道什么窃龙贼的事
All right, look, we don't know anything about a dragon thief
也不知道什么喷冰的龙 还有你那个疯子老板和他的龙族战队的事 好吗?
or an ice-spitting dragon or your lunatic boss and his dragon army, okay?
把我们的龙还回来 我们马上走...
Just give us back our dragon, and we'll go...
我们不认识你这个不怀好意的人
Strange, hostile person whom we've never met.
哦 我怎么这么没礼貌?
Oh, where are my manners?
我是艾瑞特... 艾瑞特的儿子
I'm Eret... Son of Eret.
最出色的捕龙者
Finest dragon trapper alive.
毕竟... 不是谁都能抓到一只夜煞的
After all... It's not just anyone who can capture a Night Fury.
这是没牙仔 他说我们要走了 马上就走
And this is Toothless. He says we're going. Now.
哈! 他们都说过这话
Hah! They all say that.
抓住他们 兄弟们!
Rush 'em, lads!
暴飞飞 过来! 快! 快!
Stormfly, come on! Go! Go!
你永远不可能拥有那条龙! 听到没?!
You will never hold on to those dragons! You hear me?!
德雷格要把它们全拿下!
Drago is coming for them all!
- 快点 肉丸儿! - 喔吼
- Come on, Meatlug! - Whoo-hoo!
- 嘿 斯多戈! - 嘿 你好吗? 美丽的一天啊
- Hey there, Stoick! - Hey, how are you? Beautiful day.
- 你好 斯巴洛特 比赛很棒 - 耶...
- Hello, Spitelout. Great race. - Yeah...
哦! 抱歉 阿柯夫人 有他的消息吗?
Oh! Sorry, Mrs. Ack. Any sign of him?
诶! 他现在可能已经飞到世界边缘去了
Eh! He's probably flown off the edge of the world by now.
你确定你要让那孩子来管理村子?
You sure you want that kid running the village?
- 你可以推迟退休 - 哦 他已经准备好了 你会明白的
- You can still delay your retirement. - Oh, he's ready. You'll see.
他在那儿! 哈? 博克岛的骄傲!
There he is! Huh? The pride of Berk!
最后还是决定来工作的家伙 耶
Who finally decided to show up for work. Yay.
抱歉 路上遇到点事情 嘿 老爸 我能跟你谈谈吗?
Sorry, got held up. Hey, uh, Dad, could I have a word?
有事想迫不及待地告诉我?
Something you're itching to tell me?
呃 不是你想的那个迫不及待 不过 也算是吧
Uh, not quite the itch you're thinking of, but, yes.
哦 好孩子! 现在 第一课:
Oh, good man! Now, lesson one:
一个首领最重要的职责就是他的人民 那么... 四十一号!
A chief's first duty is to his people, so... 41!
好吧 我们能不能私下里谈谈...
Well, can we just talk in private for...
- 四十... - 是我! 是我! 下一个是我!
- Forty... - That's me! That's me! I'm next!
- 嘿 我在你前面! - 如果我们能谈谈...
- Hey, I was ahead of you! - If we could just talk...
不好意思 我已经在这里等了一天了 好了 好了...
Excuse me. I've been here all day. Okay, okay...
我想要一个有很多钉子的高座位...
I want one of those high seaters with lots of spikes...
- 还有一个大的器材箱! - 当然可以! 马上给你 先生
- and a big storage compartment! - Absolutely! You got it, sir.
老爸 这事儿真的比装龙鞍要重要
Dad, this is actually a little more important than building saddles.
啊 第二课: 为人民服务没有小事
Ah, lesson two: No task is too small when it comes to serving your people.
- 但是 老爸... - 哦 不好意思 喷火龙
- But, Dad... - Oh, excuse us, grump.
- 我们能不能就谈... - 呀! 喷火龙!
- Can we just talk... - Yah! Grump!
你又让熔炉的火灭了!
You let the forge die down again!
就是这样的 喷火龙! 得把你送人了
That's it, grump! You're going up for adoption.
- 好吧 呃... - 给你
- Okay, uh... - There you go.
- 老爸... - 去吧 拿过去
- Dad... - Go on. Have away.
好吧 但是说真的 我真得和你谈谈我们发现的另一个地方
Yeah, but seriously, I really need to tell you about this new land we came across.
- 另一个? - 有新的龙吗?
- Another one? - Any new dragons?
我们没去找
We didn't stick around to find out.
那些人真的不太友善
These folks weren't particularly friendly.
哦 是吗? 你的夜煞和致命纳德没把他们...
Oh, really? Your Night Fury and Deadly Nadder didn't bring them...
- 震慑得为你欢呼? - 不 这次不一样
- cheering to the rooftops? - No, this was different.
他们不是那种一般的小强盗土匪
Not the standard run-for-the-hills hoo-ha I've come to enjoy.
他们是捕猎的 捕龙者
These guys were trappers. Dragon trappers.
你们应该见过他们的堡垒
You should have seen their fort.
被炸成了碎片冻在巨大的冰刺里面 真的非常诡异
All blown apart and stuck in giant spikes of ice. It was weird.
我从没见过那样的事 最糟的是 他们以为是我们干的
I've never seen anything like it. And worst of all, they thought we did it!
你要知道 你们两个这样子迟早会惹来大祸的
You know, you two are gonna get yourselves in serious trouble one of these days.
不是每个人都喜欢这样的生活的
Not everyone appreciates this way of life.
赞成 高博说得对 儿子 我们最好管好自己的事儿
Aye, Gobber's right, son. Best we keep to our own.
除此之外 你要把时间花在更重要的事情上 知道吗?
Besides, you'll have more important uses for your time. Huh-huh?
到时我们要弄个特大公告!
Once we make the big announcement!
他们在造龙族战队
They are building a dragon army.
或者至少是在为此准备 呃...
Or at least the guy they work for is. Uh...
"德雷格... 什么玩意" 还是什么的
"Dargo... bloody fist" or something.
他要是敢抢我的龙 我让他吃不了兜着走!
I'll bloody his fist with my face if he tries to take my dragon!
我也是!
Or mine!
- 啊! 你真是个二货 - 一个美丽的二货
- Ugh! You're such a moron. - A beautiful moron.
没错
Yeah.
布拉维斯特? 德雷格·布拉维斯特?
Bludvist? Drago Bludvist?
呃 是的 等等... 你知道他?
Uh, yeah. Wait... you know him?
- 让所有的龙都着陆! - 什么? 为什么?
- Ground all dragons! - What? Why?
关严大门! 把外门降下来!
Seal the gates! Lower the storm doors!
喔 喔 喔 等等 等等 发生了什么?
Whoa, whoa, whoa, wait, wait. What is happening?
快点! 听到了吧 快关门!
Come on! You heard the man, lock it down!
除非我下令 否则所有的龙和维京人都不能踏出这个岛半步!
No dragon or Viking sets foot off this island until I give the word!
等等 就因为某个你认识的人在很远的地方惹麻烦吗?
Wait, because some guy you knew is stirring up trouble in some faraway land?
因为德雷格·布拉维斯特是个疯子 他心狠手辣
Because Drago Bludvist is a madman without conscience or mercy.
要是他真的在组建龙族战队 我们一定得全力准备迎战
And if he's built a dragon army, gods help us all.
- 把它们关回笼子里! - 是 斯多戈
- Get them into their pens! - Aye, Stoick.
- 快点! - 那我们就飞回去
- Quickly! - Then let's ride back out there.
跟着那些抓龙的人找到德雷格 给他讲讲道理
We'll follow those trappers to Drago and talk some sense into him.
不 我们要加固防御
No. We fortify the island.
- 维护和平是我们的责任 - 没有和平了 小嗝嗝
- It's our duty to keep the peace. - Peace is over, Hiccup.
- 你要做好迎战的准备 - 迎战?
- I must prepare you for war. - War?
爸 要是德雷格来抢我们的龙 我们不能坐以待毙
Dad, if Drago's coming for our dragons, we can't wait around for him to get here.
我们去找他 劝他改变想法
Let's go find him and change his mind.
不行 有些人的想法是不会改变的 小嗝嗝
No, some minds won't be changed, Hiccup.
博克岛才是你应该担心的 首领要保护好自己的家园
Berk is what you need to worry about. A chief protects his own.
保护好龙厩 锁好围栏
Secure the stables! Latch every stall!
- 小嗝嗝 别去 - 我一定要去
- Hiccup, don't. - I have to.
这边! 快点!
This way! Quickly!
小嗝嗝!
Hiccup!
加油!
Come on!
小嗝嗝
Hiccup!
睁大眼睛 伙计们!
Keep your eyes peeled, lads!
顺着这阵风 明天天亮我们就能见到德雷格了
With this wind, we'll reach Drago by daybreak.
我们最好尽快抓几只龙放在船上!
So best we fill this ship up with dragons, and quick!
- 没时间挑挑拣拣的了! - 呃 艾瑞特?
- It's no time to be picky! - Uh, Eret?
要是想活命...
Not if we want to keep our...
在左舷船尾!
heads! Off the port quarter!
网住他们! 打下来!
Net them, lads! Take them down!
有两只! 就在左边!
There's two of them! Up on the left!
你们这次跑不了了
You're not getting away this time.
开火!
Fire!
重装!
Reload!
快点 重装! 来了!
Come on, reload! Incoming!
刚才我还担心我们可能会空手而归
And here I was, worried we might turn up empty-handed.
不会了 今天你走运
Nope. It's your lucky day.
我们投降
We give up.
这是一只夜煞 还有一只致命纳得 还有...
That's one Night Fury, uh, one Deadly Nadder, and...
西边岛上的两位驯龙高手
two of the finest Dragon Riders west of Luk Tuk.
这下你们老板该满意了吧?
That ought to make the boss happy, right?
让一下
Excuse us.
- 你这是干什么? - 没牙仔 别动
- What are you doing? - Toothless, stay.
呃 龙不太喜欢拥挤的地方
Uh, the dragons don't really care for cramped spaces,
所以它们就和你们待着吧 它们很乖的
so they'll just hang out with you. They won't be any trouble.
除非你先挑事 你也懂的 航行在大海里的木船...
Unless you do that. You know, wooden boats, big ocean...
- 你... 你们的泳技如何? - 不太好
- H... how is your swimming? - Not good.
哦 差点忘了 囚犯不能带武器
Oops. Almost forget. Can't have armed prisoners.
这算什么计划?
How is this a plan?
就是为捕龙者准备的工具而已
Just what every dragon trapper needs.
一端是涂着猛烈凶魇唾液的刀刃
One end coats the blade in Monstrous Nightmare saliva.
另一边能喷射丑陋双头龙的瓦斯气体
The other sprays hideous zippleback gas.
只需要一点火花 然后...
All it takes is a spark, and...
真棒 干得漂亮
Oh, yeah, there you go.
只要他们开始把你当做自己人
Once they see you as one of their own,
再暴躁的龙都是可以驯服的 对吧 兄弟?
even the testiest dragons can be trained. Right, bud?
把那个给我!
Give me that!
你这玩的是哪一出?
What game are you playing?
呃 我可没在玩 我们只是想见见德雷格
Uh, no game. We just want to meet Drago.
为什么?
Why?
因为我要改变他对龙的看法
Because I'm going to change his mind about dragons.
他很善于说服别人
He can be really persuasive.
只要它决定对你忠心 就可以为你赴汤蹈火
Once you've earned his loyalty, there is nothing a dragon won't do for you.
你无法改变这里任何人的想法
You won't be changing any minds around here.
我现在马上就能说服你
I can change yours, right here, right now.
可以吗?
Uh, may I?
- 当心! - 龙骑士!
- Watch it! - Dragon Riders!
放开我!
Put me down!
- 鼻涕虫 你... 你要干什么? - 看我对你多好
- Snotlout, what... what are you doing? - See how well I protect and provide?
- 这些网是干什么的? - 嘿 小心! 真是...
- What is with all the nets? - Hey, watch it! That was...
危险
Close.
天啊
Oh, my.
真是我的菜
Me likey.
带我走吧
Take me.
住手!
Hold your fire!
呃 你们来这里干什么?
Um, what are you guys doing here?
- 我们来救你! - 我用不着你们救我
- We're here to rescue you! - I don't need to be rescued.
够了!
Enough!
那个 你们是不是上错船了?
Well, didn't you just pick the wrong ship, eh?
我是艾瑞特 和我爸爸... 一个名字...
I am Eret, Son of... Eret...
我...
I...
放开我
Get this thing off me.
还有谁? 嗯 我猜到了
Anyone else? Hmm, that's what I figured.
你 准备好 我们回家
You, saddle up. We're going home.
不
No.
你这样一点责任心都没有...
Of all the irresponsible...
我想要保护我们的家园 阻止战争的发生
I'm trying to protect our dragons and stop a war.
- 这怎么就是没有责任心了? - 因为他就想要战争!
- How is that irresponsible? - Because war is what he wants, son!
许多年前 来自各地的首领聚集一堂...
Years ago, there was a great gathering of chieftains...
共同讨论如何应对大家共同的敌人 也就是龙
to discuss the dragon we all faced.
我们之中 走出一位来自遥远地方的陌生人
Into our midst came a stranger from a strange land,
他浑身伤疤 披着龙皮斗篷
covered in scars and draped in a cloak of dragon skin.
他没有武器 说话的语气也很柔和
He carried no weapon and spoke softly,
他说他叫德雷格·布拉维斯特 并非首领
saying that he, Drago Bludvist, was a man of the people,
一生致力于从龙的暴虐中解救人类
devoted to freeing mankind from the tyranny of dragons.
他说只有他可以掌控所有的龙
He claimed that he alone could control the dragons,
保护大家的安全 只要...
and that he alone could keep us safe, if...
我们臣服于他
we chose to bow down and follow him.
- 蠢货 - 笑死了
- Stupid. - Ah, good one.
是啊 我们也笑了...
Aye, we laughed, too...
直到他裹紧斗篷 喊着
Until he wrapped himself in his cloak and cried out,
- "那就看看 没有我你们能怎么办!" - 那就看看 没有我你们能怎么办!
- "then see how well you do without me!" - See how well you do without me!
房顶瞬间被点燃 身披战甲的龙
The rooftop suddenly burst into flames, and from it,
从天而降
armored dragons descended,
大火烧塌了整个房子
burning the hall to the ground.
我...
I...
是唯一的幸存者
was the only one to escape.
不问原因只管杀人的人 是没法跟他讲道理的
Men who kill without reason cannot be reasoned with.
- 也许吧 - 小嗝嗝!
- Maybe. - Hiccup!
可我还是要试试
I'm still going to try.
这是我擅长的事情 而且... 而且如果我能够说服你
This is what I'm good at, and... and if I could change your mind,
我也可以说服他
I can change his, too.
我们走
Come on.
- 我们走 - 不行! 带其他人回家
- Let's go. - No! Lead the others back to Berk.
今天的麻烦够大了
I've had enough mutiny for one day.
我好喜欢这样
Ooh, I like that.
拉芙纳特!
Ruffnut!
来了!
Okay!
别担心 伙计 我绝不会让你受到任何伤害
Don't worry, bud. I'm not gonna let anything happen to you.
我保证
I promise.
嗷 老爸 你至不至于?
Aw, come on, Dad. Really?
好吧
Okay.
别妄动
No sudden moves.
稳住 稳住
Hold on, hold on.
没牙仔...!
Toothless...!
嘿! 你把我的龙扔在那里了!
Hey! You left my dragon back there!
他自己飞不起来! 他会淹死的!
He can't fly on his own! He'll drown!
嘿! 呃...
Hey! Uh...
我们得回去找我的龙!
We have to head back for my dragon!
你是谁?
Who are you?
窃龙贼?
The dragon thief?
呃... 德雷格·布拉维斯特?
Uh... Drago Bludvist?
你听得懂我在说什么吗?
Do you even understand what I'm saying?
没牙仔! 哦 别担心 没事了 没事了
Toothless! Oh, it's okay, it's okay, it's okay.
我也很高兴能见到你 我真的好担心
I'm glad to see you, too, bud. You really had me worried there.
呃 呃...
Uh, uh...
哦...
Oh...
你是小嗝嗝?
Hiccup?
嗯...
Uh...
真... 真的吗?
C... could it be?
这么多年过去了? 这怎么可能?
After all these years? How is this possible?
那个... 我们认识吗?
Uh, should I... Should I know you?
你不认识我 你那时还是个婴儿
No. You were only a babe.
但是妈妈永远忘不掉自己的孩子
But a mother never forgets.
嘘 嘘
Shh, shh.
跟我来
Come.
脾气太倔了! 和他妈妈一样!
Boar-headed! Just like his mother!
- 是啊 她也是个闲不住的人 - 他毕竟才二十岁 还是维京人
- Aye, she could never stay put, either. - Eh, he's just 20, and a Viking.
还有更差的组合吗? 哈哈!
I mean, could there be a worse combination? Heh!
何况你年轻的时候还不是一样的固执又不懂事
When I think of how stubborn and senseless you were back in the day.
其实 现在也没好多少
Oh. Well, not much has changed, actually.
你也知道他的 他绝不会放弃 高博
Ah, you know what he's like. He won't give up, Gobber.
如果小嗝嗝在我们之前找到了德雷格...
And if Hiccup finds Drago before we find him...
不会的! 只要小嗝嗝身边有那只夜煞 没人伤得了他
Ah! Nothing can hurt Hiccup, as long as that Night Fury's around.
那可是夜煞啊!
It's a Night Fury!
嗯?
Huh?
帮我找到他们 碎颅
Find them, Skullcrusher.
去找他们
Find them.
- 呃 等... 等下 - 来这边
- Uh, h... hold on. Wait just a minute. - This way.
- 回来 - 过来
- Come back here. - Come.
你不能说出那么惊人的话就跑开吧
You can't just say something like that and run off.
你是我妈妈?! 这到底...?
You're my mother?! I mean, what the...?
你... 你知道这听起来有多疯狂吗?
Do you... do you grasp how insane it sounds?
- 快点过来 - 我有问题要问你!
- Come quickly. - I have questions!
你这些年... 都在哪里?
Where have you... been all this time?
你... 你都做些什么? 他们... 他们都说你已经死了!
What... what have you been doing? But they... they said you were dead!
大家都觉得你被龙吃了...
Everyone thinks you were eaten by...
你就是在这里生活了二十年?
This is where you've been for 20 years?
你... 你一直在拯救他们
You... you've been rescuing them.
- 真不敢相信 - 你不生气吗?
- Unbelievable. - You're not upset?
什么? 我... 我也不知道 我...
What? No. I... I don't know. I...
说实话 我还没太反应过来呢
It's a bit much to get my head around, to be frank.
毕竟 也不是每天你都会发现 你老妈其实是个...
It's not every day you find out your mother is some kind of...
有点吓人的龙族守护者
crazy, feral, vigilante dragon lady.
哦...
Oh...
这样来说...
Well...
至少我不是个无聊的人 对吧?
At least I'm not boring, right?
这一点...
Well, I suppose there is that...
- 倒是没错 - 你... 你喜欢这样吗?
- one specific thing. - Do... do you like it?
我... 我不知道该怎么说
I... I don't have the words.
我... 我能摸摸它吗...
C... can I...
哦 他真漂亮
Oh, he's beautiful. Oh.
萌得难以置信
Oh, incredible.
他可能是这个种群的最后一只龙了
He might very well be the last of his kind.
哦... 看啊 他和你一样大
Oh... and look, he's your age.
哇哦
Wow.
难怪你们这么合得来 什么? 真的吗?
No wonder you get along so well. Oh, yeah? Oh, yeah?
他的牙可以收回去
And retractable teeth.
- 你是怎么能... - 我是在树林里找到的它
- How did you manage... - I found him in the woods.
他当时受伤了
He was shot down and wounded.
暴牙被德雷格·布拉维斯特的铁制陷阱夹断了一条腿
This Snafflefang lost his leg to one of Drago Bludvist's iron traps.
削雨的翅膀被剃刀网划伤了
This Raincutter had her wing sliced by razor netting.
这只可怜的拐哼哼被树枝陷阱弄瞎了...
And this, oh, poor Hobblegrunt was blinded by a tree snare...
在孤单和恐惧中等死
and then left to die alone and scared.
这个呢? 也是被德雷格和他的陷阱害的?
And what of this? Did Drago or his trappers do this, too?
说到这个
Oh. Yeah.
也算是挺巧的...
Well, crazy thing is...
是我把他打伤的
I'm actually the one who shot him down.
嘿 不过... 现在没事了 他也报复我了
Hey, it's... it's okay, though. He got me back.
对不对 伙计? 你偏偏不肯快点救我 对不对?
Right, bud? You couldn't save all of me, could you?
非要跟我算账 所以我的腿才断了
You just had to make it even. So peg leg.
你老爸对你的夜煞小伙伴什么态度?
What did your father think of your Night Fury friend?
哦 他... 他一开始不太接受
Oh, he... he didn't take it all that well.
不过后来 他就变了 他们都变了
But then, he changed. They all did.
很快 家乡的每个人都有一只属于自己的龙了
Pretty soon, everyone back home had dragons of their own.
- 要是真的就好了 - 就是真的啊
- If only it were possible. - No, really.
相信我 我也试过 但是人们很难改变的 小嗝嗝
Believe me, I tried, as well, but people are not capable of change, Hiccup.
有些人...
Some of us...
生来就注定与众不同
were just born different.
那时候 博克岛面临生死存亡的抉择
Berk was a land of kill or be killed,
但我相信和平的希望尚存
but I believed peace was possible.
住手! 你这样只能让事情越来越糟!
Stop! You'll only make it worse!
当时没人愿意听我的
It was a very unpopular opinion.
小嗝嗝!
Hiccup!
后来有一天晚上 一条龙闯进我们家里
Then one night, a dragon broke into our house,
找到了摇篮中的你
finding you in the cradle.
我冲过去想要保护你
I rushed to protect you.
但是我看到的一切 证明我的想法是对的
But what I saw was proof of everything I believed.
它不是什么邪恶的野兽 而是聪明温和的生物
This wasn't a vicious beast, but an intelligent, gentle creature,
我们的灵魂可以产生共鸣
whose soul reflected my own.
- 沃尔卡 快跑! - 不 别这样
- Valka, run! - No, don't.
哦...
Oh...
等等!
Hold on!
- 不! 斯多戈! - 沃尔卡!
- No! Stoick! - Valka!
斯多戈!
Stoick!
沃尔卡
Valka.
那天晚上你和你父亲差点丧命
You and your father nearly died that night.
都是因为我不愿意死杀死一条龙
All because I couldn't kill a dragon.
呃 这好像是基因决定的
Eh, runs in the family.
和你们分开 我也难过 但是我觉得这样你们才安全
It broke my heart to stay away, but I believed you'd be safer if I did.
你是怎么活下来的?
How did you survive?
哦 跃云并没想伤害我
Oh, Cloudjumper never meant to harm me.
他一定是觉得我本来就属于这里...
He must have thought I belonged here...
这个美丽的野兽之家
in the home of the great Bewilderbeast.
阿尔法一族
The Alpha species.
已经濒临灭绝了
One of the very few that still exist.
每个龙巢都有龙后 但这是万龙之王
Every nest has its queen, but this is the king of all dragons.
他能喷出冰 建造了我们这个美丽的家园
With his icy breath, this graceful giant built our nest,
成为所有龙的栖身之所
a safe haven for dragons everywhere.
等下 它就是会喷冰的龙? 那个堡垒就是他毁掉的?
Wait, that's the ice-spitter? He's responsible for all that destruction?
他在保护我们
He protects us.
我们受他庇护 并听命于他
We all live under his care and his command.
当然 除了那些龙宝宝...
All but the babies, of course...
他们谁的话都不听
who listen to no one.
小嗝嗝 我和他们生活了二十年了
I've lived among them for 20 years, Hiccup,
探索他们的秘密
discovering their secrets.
- 他喜欢你 - 哇哦
- He likes you. - Wow.
你肯定饿了
You must be hungry.
- 呃 有点饿了 - 太好了 是时候吃饭了
- Uh, yeah, I could eat. - Good. It's feeding time.
我不开心 他们现在应该已经带着小嗝嗝回来了
I don't like it. They should've been back with Hiccup by now.
我也不开心 艾瑞特 和父亲同名的艾瑞特是我的梦中情人
I don't like it, either. Eret, Son of Eret, was the man of my dreams.
我的一切!
My everything!
- 可是 宝贝 我都为你留胡子了 - 我也是
- But, baby, I grew facial hair for you. - Me, too.
要是德雷格抓住他们了怎么办? 要是他们需要帮助怎么办?
What if Drago shot them down? What if they need our help?
- 我们得去找他们 - 等下 你说什么?
- We have to find them. - Wait, wait, what?
- 不行 斯多戈说... - 要是他们都被抓了
- No, but Stoick said... - It doesn't matter what he said
他说过什么就不重要了 走吧!
if they've all been captured. Come on!
- 我们还回去吗? - 我们无处可去...
- Do we go back? - We've nowhere to go...
空手而归 等着我们的好下场
nothing to sell, and no heads to call our own.
假如我们不快点追上那些龙...
If we don't turn up with dragons and fast...
- 当心自己许的愿望哦! - 帮帮我!
- Careful what you wish for! - Do something!
- 艾瑞特 - 我们会想你的 艾瑞特!
- Eret, Son of Eret! - We'll miss you, Eret!
- 你这是干嘛? - 绑架
- What is this? - A kidnapping.
耶 他可以和我一起吗? 可以吗?
Yay, can he ride with me? Can he?
可以吗...?
Can he...?
你带路 带我们去找德雷格
You're gonna show us the way to Drago.
然后让龙骑士溜进德雷格的营地? 还不如杀了我
And help Dragon Riders sneak into Drago's camp? Just kill me now.
可以呀 暴飞飞 扔掉
That could be arranged. Stormfly, drop it.
啊?
Huh?
好孩子!
Good girl!
暴飞飞 捡回来
Stormfly, fetch.
好吧! 我带你们去找德雷格
All right! Okay! I'll take you to Drago!
屡试不爽
Works every time.
嘿 我... 我以为我们要去吃东西
Hey, I... I thought we were going to eat.
哦 是啊
Oh, we are.
然后 从龙之岛 我找到了这群岛
And then, from Dragon Island, I found this archipelago...
在那里
There.
哇
Whoa.
在天上飞的时候 我甚至都不觉得寒冷
Oh, when I'm up here, I don't even feel the cold.
- 只觉得... - 自由
- I just feel... - Free.
这就是当一条龙的感受 小嗝嗝
This is what it is to be a dragon, Hiccup.
说自己是龙没问题 但是你会飞吗?
It's all well and good to call yourself a dragon, but can you fly?
哦 不!
Oh, no!
老天 差一点
Man, almost!
我们差一点就成功了
We just about had it that time.
难以置信
Incredible.
你也不赖
Well, not bad yourself.
过去这么久了 你还是这么像我
All this time, you took after me.
可是... 我又在哪里?
And... where was I?
对不起 小嗝嗝 我们重新来过吧?
I'm so sorry, Hiccup. Can we start over?
你愿意再给妈妈一次机会吗?
Will you give me another chance?
我... 我可以把我这二十年来学到的都教给你
I... I can teach you all that I've learned these past 20 years.
比如...
Like...
哇
Wow.
现在你可以控制他们的急转弯了
Now you can make those tight turns.
你知道这个?
Did you know about this?
每条龙都有它的秘密...
Every dragon has its secrets. And...
我会把它们都告诉你
I'll show them all to you.
我们能解开所有秘密 找到每个珍稀物种... 我们一起
We'll unlock every mystery, find every last species... together,
妈妈和儿子一起
as mother and son.
我们都有这种天赋 小嗝嗝 这让我们母子连心
This gift we share, Hiccup, it bonds us.
这才是你 儿子
This is who you are, son.
这才是真正的我们
Who we are.
为所有的龙 我们会改变这个世界
We will change the world for all dragons.
让这个世界更美好 更安全
We will make it a better, safer place.
是啊 听起来真不可思议
Yeah, I mean, that sounds amazing.
噢 太好了! 现在我们可以一起去和德雷格谈判了
Oh, this is so great! Now you and I can go talk to Drago together.
什么? 没有什么谈判
What? There's no talking to Drago.
- 但是我们得... - 没有
- But we have to... - No.
我们要保护好我们自己
We must protect our own.
快点 我们该回去了
Come on. We should be getting back.
嗯?
Hmm?
好了! 我把你们带来了 放开我
Okay! I got you here. Now get this thing off me.
千万别和龙抢玩具 你什么道理都不懂吗?
Never take a toy from a dragon. Don't you know anything?
为什么总是我倒霉?
Why does this keep happening to me?
那下面是什么东西?
What's down there?
巨大的气泡 说明有巨大的肺 冷水深海生物
Large diameter bubbles, massive lungs, cold water deep dweller,
我想这是五级的海怪 或者是六级
I'm thinking class five leviathan, maybe six.
啊!
Yah!
- 肉丸儿 怎么了 孩子? - 来吧
- Meatlug, what's wrong, girl? - Come on!
- 别动! - 啊...
- Don't move! - Uh...
德雷格!
Drago!
放开我!
Get off me!
总是很高兴见到你 朋友 还在热身呢?
Always great to see you, my friend. Keeping warm up here?
你看到了 我准时带着一批龙来了
Well, as you can see, I am right on time with a new batch of dragons,
我兑现承诺了
just like I promised.
- 它醒了! - 把绳子扔掉!
- He's waking up! - Drop the ropes!
- 来人帮帮忙! - 小心!
- Give me some backup here! - Watch out!
放下绳子
Drop the ropes.
- 钩牙！ - 你在干什么?!
- Hookfang! - What are you doing?!
你现在属于我了
You belong to me now.
额外惊喜 我也把它们的骑士给你抓来了 不要回报
And as an added bonus, I also caught you their riders. No extra charge.
- 什么? 你在开玩笑? - 啊! 但是你那么完美!
- What? Are you kidding me? - Aw! But you were so perfect!
结果那里还有很多龙和骑士
Turns out there's a whole bunch of them out there.
他们攻击了...
They attacked...
- 有多少? - 还好德雷格没有抓住他们
- How many? - Drago doesn't have them after all.
- 多少? - 上百个 整个岛都是
- How many? - Hundreds. A whole island full.
我不担心那个
I wouldn't worry about it.
我们说话的功夫 我的人就在追杀他们
My men are hunting them down as we speak.
他们不会知道你躲在哪里 我保证
They won't know where you're hiding. I promise you that.
他们会的! 他们知道我们不见了 而且他们有警龙
Oh, yes, they will! They know we're missing, and they have tracking dragons.
只要你们敢动我们分毫
If you so much as touch us,
- 小嗝嗝就会把你... - 小嗝嗝?
- Hiccup is gonna kick... - Hiccup?
他不成问题 真的 相信我
He's not a problem. Really, trust me.
他是伟大的斯多戈的独子 博克岛首领的继承人
He's only the son of Stoick The Vast, his heir to the throne of Berk,
世界上迄今为止最伟大的驯龙师
and the greatest Dragon Master this world has ever seen.
"驯龙师"? 只有我才能控制龙
"Dragon Master"? I alone control the dragons.
- 嗯...不是 - 不好意思啦!
- Nope, mm-mm. - Sorry!
除非你们现在就放我们走 不然他会带着他的夜煞赶到这里
And unless you let us go right now, he will blast through here on his Night Fury
把你们整个船队打个片甲不留
and blow your entire fleet of ships to splinters.
他们会哭的和孩子一样
Then they'll be crying like babies.
- 又棒又有意思 - 不错 宝贝
- Funny and beautiful. - Good one, babe.
像小孩一样 一直哭 不能再小的小孩
Like babies, they always cry. Real tiny ones.
一开始只有一个骑士
First there was one rider,
现在整个博克岛都是了?
And now all of Berk?
你还把他们带我这来!
And you led them to me!
- 德雷格...! - 停止所有备战!
- Drago...! - Stop all preparations!
我们必须现在就去攻打龙骑士们的老巢!
We must attack the Dragon Riders' nest at once!
把他们的阿尔法打败
We will take down their Alpha.
然后占领博克岛!
Then we will take Berk!
- 德雷格! - 干掉他
- Drago! - And get rid of him.
求你了 德雷格 我...
Drago, please, I...
暴飞飞!
Stormfly!
不!
No!
老兄...我们不能坐以待毙等着德雷格来攻打
Well, bud... We can't wait around for Drago to attack this place.
我们得先找到他
We've got to find him first.
走吧
Let's go.
淡定 淡定
Easy now.
你开什么玩笑? 你怎么进来的?
Are you kidding me? How did you get in here?
怎么带你出去 我们就怎么进来的
The same way we're getting you out.
- "我们?" - 安全
- "We"? - All clear.
- 没牙仔 跟上 - 额 等等 等等
- Toothless, come. - Uh, wait, uh, wait...
好吧 额 老爸 还有... 还有些事情你不知道
Okay, uh, Dad, there... there's something you need to know.
好的 好的 路上说
Yeah, yeah, tell me on the way.
这事可不适合"在路上"说
Well, this isn't an "on the way" kind of update, actually.
这话我听够了 小嗝嗝
I've heard enough, Hiccup.
惊天动地的变化越来越多了
More of the earth-shattering development variety.
- 好的 等等再说  - 好的 我 额... 嗯...
- Yeah, just add it to pile. - Yeah, I, uh... uh...
老爸 不像给你的大多数惊喜 我保证你会喜欢这个的
Dad, unlike most surprises I spring on you, this is one you'll like, I promise.
你先控制好情绪 然后...
You just have to handle it delicately. So...
呃...
Uh...
可能得要你来搞定这事
You might want to take this one.
啊?
Huh?
天啊
Oh, boy.
哦 呃 老爸 你先把剑放一边去好不好?
Oh, uh, Dad, could you put the sword away, please?
我知道你要说什么 斯多戈
I know what you're gonna say, Stoick.
我怎么可以这样?
How could I have done this?
在外这么多年 为什么我不回你身边?
Stayed away all of these years, and why didn't I come back to you?
回儿子身边?
To our son?
可是... 你有改变的迹象吗 斯多戈?
Well... what sign did I have that you could change, Stoick?
还是博克岛的人有改变的迹象?
That anyone on Berk could?
我恳求停战那么多次
I pleaded so many times to stop the fighting,
找其他解决方式 你们有谁听了吗?
to find another answer, but did any of you listen?
这就是我不结婚的原因 这个和另外一个原因
This is why I never married. This, and one other reason.
我知道我撇下你一人抚养小嗝嗝不容易
I know that I left you to raise Hiccup alone,
但是我觉得没有我他生活得更好
but I thought he'd be better off without me,
但是我错了 我知道了 但是...
and I was wrong. I see that now, but...
哦! 别再忍着了 斯多戈
Oh! Stop being so stoic, Stoick.
来吧 吼我 骂我 说句话啊!
Go on, shout, scream, say something!
你还是美如昨日
You're as beautiful as the day I lost you.
- 还能更惨吗? - 嗯 让我看看
- Could this day get any worse? - Uh, let me see.
我们要跳到冰冷的海水里淹死
We're gonna jump into freezing cold water and then die from drowning.
看起来还不错
Looks refreshing.
女士优先
Please, ladies first.
你真是一坨...
You are a steaming...
- 热气腾腾的龙... - 低头
- heap of dragon... - Duck.
- 通知大家! - 干掉他们 艾瑞特的儿子
- Warn the others! - Get them, you son of an Eret.
尝尝这个!
Take that!
好吧 我又爱你了
Okay, I love you again.
哦 真可怜 你还是继续跳下去吧
Oh, pathetic. You can still jump.
那么我们还把龙救出来然后逃出去吗?
So, are we going to save your dragons and get out of here or not?
嗯
Mm.
检查每个笼子 它们肯定都在船上
Check every trap. They're here somewhere.
肉丸儿?
Meatlug?
有人想进去吗?
Anyone coming?
不知道 你继续就好
I don't know, you just keep doing what you're doing.
继续转呀
Keep cranking.
多谢你救了我一命
Thank you for saving my life.
现在我该还你人情了
Now let me return the favor.
妈妈 你肯定都认不出这里了
Mom, you'd never even recognize it.
本来是造武器的地方 现在我们做龙鞍了
Where we used to make weapons, we now build saddles,
翼吊带... 我们甚至还给龙补牙
wing slings... We even fix dragon teeth.
这些变化让你难以置信
You wouldn't believe how much everything's changed.
是的 你儿子让博克岛变得更好了
Aye, your son's changed Berk for the better.
咱儿子是我们的杰作 沃尔
I think we did well with this one, Val.
谢谢 老爸
Thanks, Dad.
我来吧
I got it.
我... 有点生疏了
I'm, uh... a little out of practice.
嗯 我娶你本来就不是看上你的厨艺
Well, you know, I didn't marry you for your cooking.
但愿 她做的肉丸的杀伤力比战斧还大
I hope not. Her meatballs could kill more beasts than a battle ax.
我现在肚子还在响呢
I've still got a few knocking around in here.
你和你的龙只要一搬回来住
And once you move back in with all your dragons,
老德雷格就一点机会都没有了
old Drago won't even stand a chance.
- 一切都会好起来  - 等等 儿子
- Everything will be okay. - Slow down, son.
还有好多事情要适应呢
It's a lot to take in.
哦 我知道了
Oh, gotcha.
我可喜欢这歌了
Oh, I love this one.
还记得我们的歌吗 沃尔?
Remember our song, Val?
∮ 在凶猛大海上徜徉远航 ∮
∮ I'll swim and sail on savage seas ∮
∮ 永不畏惧沉没还是受伤 ∮
∮ With ne'er a fear of drowning ∮
∮ 欢欣鼓舞踏着生活波浪 ∮
∮ And gladly ride the waves of life ∮
∮ 假如你愿意当我的新娘 ∮
∮ If you will marry me ∮
∮ 头顶再无烈烈骄阳 ∮
∮ No scorching sun ∮
∮ 脚下不踩冰封一方 ∮
∮ Nor freezing cold ∮
- ∮ 截住... ∮ - ∮ 截住我散漫的流放 ∮
- ∮ Will stop... ∮ - ∮ Will stop me on my journey ∮
抱歉
Sorry.
∮ 你若将心托付于我 ∮
∮ If you will promise me your heart ∮
∮ 并爱... ∮
∮ And love... ∮
∮ 并爱我永久不相忘 ∮
∮ And love me for eternity ∮
∮ 我最亲爱的宝贝 ∮
∮ My dearest one, my darling dear ∮
∮ 海誓山盟让我惊喜万分 ∮
∮ Your mighty words astound me ∮
∮ 但那些誓言不一定要成真 ∮
∮ But I've no need of mighty deeds ∮
∮ 有你臂弯环绕就是天堂 ∮
∮ when I feel your arms around me ∮
∮ 带给你戒指闪闪耀金光 ∮
∮ But I would bring you rings of gold ∮
- ∮ 为你唱诗在心中流淌 ∮ - 哇! 哦 你会吗?
- ∮ I'd even sing you poetry ∮ - Whoo! Oh, would you?
∮ 让你远离所有悲伤 ∮
∮ And I would keep you from all harm ∮
∮ 只要永远在我身旁 ∮
∮ if you would stay beside me ∮
∮ 何必带那戒指闪耀金光 ∮
∮ I have no use for rings of gold ∮
∮ 不必唱诗在我心中流淌 ∮
∮ I care not for your poetry ∮
∮ 只要抓住你的手牢牢不放 ∮
∮ I only want your hand to hold ∮
∮ 只要你在我身旁 ∮
∮ I only want you near me ∮
∮ 爱你吻你朝思暮想 ∮
∮ To love and kiss, to sweetly hold ∮
∮ 在梦里舞蹈飞翔 ∮
∮ For the dancing and the dreaming ∮
∮ 穿过悲欢离合 让你笑容留在我心上 ∮
∮ Through all my sorrows and delights I'll keep your laugh inside me ∮
∮ 在凶猛大海上徜徉远航 永不畏惧沉没还是受伤 ∮
∮ I'll swim and sail the savage seas with ne'er a fear of drowning ∮
∮ 欢欣鼓舞踏着生活波浪 只要你愿意当我的新娘 ∮
∮ And gladly ride the waves of life if you will marry me... ∮
- 我还能唱...没气儿了 - 高博
- I'm still going... I'm done. - Gobber.
我还以为这辈子也不能再跳一次这舞了
I thought I'd have to die before we'd have that dance again.
别这么消极
No need for drastic measures.
为了你 亲爱的...
For you, my dear...
什么都愿意
anything.
你愿意回家吗 沃尔?
Will you come home, Val?
你愿意再次做我的妻子吗?
Will you be my wife once again?
我们可以组成一个家庭! 你说呢?
We can be a family! What do you say?
这个嘛...
Well...
愿意...
Yes...
好棒! 我来做饭
Great! I'll do the cooking.
幸好你没听我的 儿子
Thank Odin you didn't listen to me, son.
不然我们永远都见不到了
We never would've found each other.
怎么了 没牙仔?
Toothless?
出了什么事?
What's happening?
噢 不...
Oh, no...
沃尔... 沃尔 没事的 没事的
Val... Val, it's all right, it's all right.
我们现在在一起 你想怎么办?
We're a team now. Now, what do you want to do?
- 我们得救救这些龙 - 是 说得对 来吧 儿子!
- We have to save the dragons. - Aye, you got it. Come on, son!
装弹!
Reload!
开火!
Fire!
开火! 开火!
Fire! Fire!
不管来了什么 持续攻打那座山
Whatever comes, keep hitting the Mountain.
我们要把阿尔法引出来
We need to draw the Alpha out.
准备陷阱!
Ready the traps!
惊喜! 耶!
Surprise! Yeah!
什么?!
What?!
你真是让我们惊喜不断啊 我们走
You really are full of surprises. Let's go.
龙骑士登场!
Dragon Riders coming through!
开火!
Fire!
耶!
Yeah!
截住他们!
Cut them down!
艾瑞特 救我!
Eret, Son of Eret!
向上 孩子!
Up, girl!
左倾 艾瑞特! 对了!
Lean left, Eret! That's it!
小心!
Look out!
耶! 宝贝!
Yeah, baby!
把他们打下来!
Take them down!
注意点喽!
Heads up!
驯龙师
Dragon Master.
- 欢迎来到战场 龙骑士 - 多谢
- Welcome aboard, Dragon Rider. - Thanks. I think.
- 你去哪里了? - 噢 和我妈妈在一起
- Where have you been? - Oh, you know, catching up with Mom.
那是你妈妈?!
That's your mother?!
没错 现在你知道我从哪遗传的天赋了吧
Well, now you know where I get my dramatic flair.
是阿尔法! 我们终于能打一仗了!
The Alpha! Now we have a fight!
上啊 没牙仔 给他们看看你的本事 兄弟
Come on, Toothless. Show them what you got, bud.
好样的!
Attaboy!
- 我已经等了太长时间了 - 你不能掳走我们的龙!
- I've waited a long time for this. - You cannot take our dragons!
阿尔法才是它们的王!
They are controlled by the Alpha!
那正好 我把夺位者带来了
Then it's a good thing I brought a challenger.
又来一个大的?
Another one?
不得了了! 不得了了!
That is a class ten! Class ten!
- 不... 不... - 给我上! 把阿尔法打败!
- No... no... - Come on! Take down the Alpha!
- 谢谢 - 亲爱的 为了你 怎样都行
- Thank you. - For you, my dear... anything.
- 沃尔 你能阻止他们吗? - 我会尽我所能 出发 跃云!
- Val, do you think you can stop them? - I'll do my best. Come on, Cloudjumper!
你!
You!
我亲眼看着你烧死的!
I watched you burn!
那么点小火还想烧死我!
It takes more than a little fire to kill me!
斯多戈!
Stoick!
不!
No!
我们赢了 现在...
We've won. Now...
- 杀了她! - 不!
- Finish her! - No!
坚持住! 碎颅 出发!
Hold on! Skullcrusher, go!
- 跟上 高博! - 马上 斯多戈!
- Come on, Gobber! - Right behind you, Stoick!
住手!
Stop!
你... 你就是所谓的驯龙师?
This... is the great Dragon Master?
伟大的斯多戈的儿子?
The son of Stoick the Vast?
他该有多羞愧啊
What shame he must feel.
所有这些龙的牺牲... 都是为了什么?
All of this loss... and for what?
为了证明你所向无敌? 为了统治世界?
To become unstoppable? To rule the world?
龙是善良 神奇的生物 能让人类更加团结
Dragons, the... they are kind, amazing creatures that can bring people together.
也能摧毁人类
Or tear them apart.
我知道 生活在恐惧中是什么感觉
You see, I know what it is to live in fear,
我亲眼看见我的村庄被烧光 我的家庭被拆散
to see my village burned, my family taken.
但即使我只是个孩子...
But even as a boy...
当时一无所有
left with nothing,
我仍然发誓要超越对龙的恐惧...
I vowed to rise above the fear of dragons...
解放这个世界上的所有人
and liberate the people of this world.
那你为什么需要一支龙族战队?
Then why a dragon army?
我需要龙来要想征服龙
Well, you need dragons to conquer other dragons.
应该是你需要龙来征服人类吧...
Or maybe you need dragons to conquer people...
去控制那些听话的...
to control those who follow you...
消灭那些不听话的
and to get rid of those who won't.
真是聪明的孩子
Clever boy.
世界需要和平
The world wants peace,
而在博克岛有你要的答案 只需要...
and we have the answer back on Berk. Just...
- 让我带你去看...  - 不!
- let me show you... - No!
还是让我... 带你看看!
Let me... show you!
怎么...
What in...
小嗝嗝!
Hiccup!
跟上 高博!
Come on, Gobber!
现在 计划变了
Okay, change of plan.
所有龙都必须服从阿尔法的命令
No dragon can resist the Alpha's command.
也就是说谁能够控制阿尔法...
So he who controls the Alpha...
谁就能统领所有的龙
controls them all.
没牙仔?
Toothless?
没牙仔 你还好么 兄弟? 怎么了?
Toothless, you okay, bud? What's going on?
见证真正的力量
Witness true strength.
控制一切的意志力
The strength of will over others.
面对事实吧 你什么都不是
In the face of it, you are nothing.
呃... 他刚才跟你说什么了?
Uh... what did he just tell you?
没牙仔 不要这样 你怎么了?
Toothless, come on. What's the matter with you?
不 不 不 不 快清醒 你在干什么? 停下来
No, no, no, no, come on, what are you doing? Knock it off.
停! 快清醒!
Stop! Snap out of it!
没牙仔 不! 没牙仔!
Toothless, no! Toothless!
- 不要! - 小嗝嗝!
- Don't! - Hiccup!
- 停! - 儿子!
- Stop...! - Son!
爸爸! 不!
Dad! No!
啊
Hmm.
不...
No...
爸爸!
Dad!
斯多戈...
Stoick...
爸爸? 不 你...
Dad? No. You...
不
No.
不 不 不 不
No, no, no. No.
不! 离他远点!
No! Get away from him!
快走! 快滚开!
Go on! Get out of here!
滚开!
Get away!
这不是他的错 你心里明白的
It's not his fault. You know that.
如今善良的龙被邪恶的人统治...
Good dragons under the control of bad people...
会做出邪恶的事情
do bad things.
精神点!
Come on!
把人都聚集起来 到博克岛与我会合!
Gather the men and meet me at Berk!
- 没牙仔! - 不 别去
- Toothless! - No, don't.
愿战神迎接你 带你走出欧丁神的伟大战场
May the Valkyries welcome you and lead you through Odin's great battlefield.
愿他们带着爱与愤怒唱出你的名字
May they sing your name with love and fury,
这样我们就能从瓦尔哈拉殿堂的深处听见
so that we might hear it rise from the depths of Valhalla,
我们就能知道你已找到你在众国王中的席位
and know that you've taken your rightful place at the table of kings.
一个伟大的人逝世了
For a great man has fallen.
他是一名战士
A warrior.
是首领 是父亲
A chieftain. A father.
是挚友
A friend.
对不起 爸爸
I'm sorry, Dad.
我不是... 你所希望的那样的首领
I'm not the chief that... you wanted me to be.
我也不是自己想象的那种和平使者
And I'm not the peacekeeper I thought I was.
我... 我不知道...
I... don't know...
生你的时候早产 刚出生时真的太小
You came early into this world. You were such a wee thing.
噢 那么瘦小 那么虚弱
Oh, so frail, so fragile.
我担心能不能把你养活
I feared you wouldn't make it.
但是你的父亲...
But your father...
他从未怀疑过
he never doubted.
他一直说你能成为所有人中最强大的那个
He always said you'd become the strongest of them all.
他说得没错
And he was right.
你拥有一颗首领的心 拥有龙的灵魂
You have the heart of a chief, and the soul of a dragon.
只有你能团结整个世界
Only you can bring our worlds together.
这... 就是你 儿子
That... is who you are, son.
我 呃...
I, uh...
我曾经害怕成为父亲那样的人
I was so afraid of becoming my dad.
因为我觉得我永远都做不到
Mostly because I thought I never could.
要怎么... 怎么才能成为一个...
How... how do you become someone...
那样伟大 那样... 勇敢
that great, that... brave,
那样... 无私的人?
that... selfless?
那就只能好好努力了
I guess you can only try.
首领要保护好族人
A chief protects his own.
我们回去
We're going back.
- 呃... 怎么回去? - 呃 他把所有的龙都带走了
- Uh... with what? - Uh, he took all the dragons.
并不是所有的
Not all of them.
哇!
Whoa!
- 哇! - 哇 哇 哇 哇 哇!
- Whoa! - Whoa, whoa, whoa, whoa!
我不想死!
I don't want to die!
- 这些真的是没法骑啊! - 就是啊 真的没法骑!
- We can't fly these things! - Yeah, no kidding!
难道万兽之王不会也把它们控制住吗?
But won't that Bewilderbeast just take control of these guys, too?
它们还是小宝宝! 它们不会听任何人的
They're babies! They don't listen to anyone.
是啊 跟我们一样
Yeah. Just like us.
这真是... 哇! 太危险了!
This is... whoa!... very dangerous!
有人可能会觉得这真不是什么好计划!
Some might suggest this is poorly conceived!
我的优点就是从来就不听话
Well, it's a good thing that I never listen.
哇!
Whoa!
那... 你到底...
So... what is your...
什么计划啊?
plan?
把没牙仔夺回来 打败德雷格...
Get Toothless back and kick Drago's...
抬头!
Heads up!
还有 小心
And that thing.
哇... 喔!
Whoa... ow!
啊 真是好孩子
Ah, that's a good boy.
小心家具!
Watch the furniture!
你去哪里?
Where are you going?
你们的首领... 死了!
Your chief... is dead!
- 斯多戈死了? - 不可能!
- Stoick? - Not possible!
现在没有人能够保护你们了!
No one can protect you now!
不好
No.
他收走了所有龙
He took all the dragons.
分散他的注意力 把他从没牙仔那引开
Distract the Alpha. Try to keep his focus off of Toothless.
呃 怎么实施?
Uh, how?
你忘了你骑着什么吗?
Have you forgotten who you're riding with?
这世上还没有我不能驾驭的龙!
There isn't a dragon alive that I can't wrangle!
- 除了这个...! - 真业余
- Except for this one...! - Amateur.
嘿 快看! 是小嗝嗝!
Hey, look! It's Hiccup!
什么?
What?
- 不停地送羊过来! - 来头黑的 宝贝!
- Keep 'em coming! - Black sheep, baby!
十分!
Ten points!
啊哦
Uh-oh.
我没事!
I'm okay!
看来你确实是很难摆脱啊
You certainly are hard to get rid of, I'll say that.
没牙仔...
Toothless...
嘿
Hey.
是我 兄弟
It's me, bud.
是我啊 是我 我就在这儿 兄弟
It's me. It's me. I'm right here, bud.
快回到我身边
Come back to me.
他不再属于你了 他只听从阿尔法的
He's not yours anymore. He belongs to the Alpha.
但是 伟大的驯龙师 您请
But, please, o great Dragon Master,
用您最大的劲儿召唤他
try... to take him.
他可不想错过第二次
He will not miss a second time.
那不是你的错 兄弟
It wasn't your fault, bud.
是他们... 强迫你的
They... made you do it.
你从来没有伤害过父亲
You'd never hurt him.
你也从来没有伤害过我
You'd never hurt me.
怎么样了?
How are you doing that?
求你了 你是我最好的朋友 兄弟
Please. You are my best friend, bud.
我最好的朋友
My best friend.
干得漂亮! 就是这样! 我在这儿
Attaboy! That's it! I'm here.
不!
No!
啊哦!
Yeehaw!
等着!
Hang on!
快了 兄弟 我马上就到了
Almost there, buddy, almost there.
快做些什么啊!
Do something!
我们需要把他们俩分开
We need to get those two apart.
我们必须阻止他 没牙仔 你信任我吗 兄弟?
We gotta block him out, Toothless. Do you trust me, bud?
我们一定可以
We can do this.
你... 和我... 我们合二为一
You... and me... as one.
就是这样 现在我们再试一次!
That's it. Now let's try this one more time!
打败他 亲爱的!
Take him down, babe!
把他拿下!
Go get him.
控制它!
Take control of it!
不要受干扰 没牙仔
Shut it out, Toothless.
- 阻止他们! - 就是现在!
- Stop them! - Now!
又来
Not again.
没牙仔 成败在此一举!
Toothless, it's now or never!
快来 兄弟!
Come on, bud!
稳住!
Hold on!
耶! 我们做到了!
Yeehaw! We did it!
看好他 没牙仔
Hold him there, Toothless.
现在一切都结束了
It's all over now.
果真如此吗?
Or is it?
噢 不!
Oh, no!
不!
No!
小嗝嗝...
Hiccup...
- 他在挑战阿尔法! - 为了保护你!
- He's challenging the Alpha! - To protect you!
不 不 不 不 不! 不!
No, no, no, no, no! No!
回击! 回击! 回击!
Fight back! Fight! Fight!
你是怎么回事!
What's the matter with you!
现在你明白了吗? 赢得了龙的忠心就是这样
Now do you get it? This is what it is to earn a dragon's loyalty.
放弃吧
Let this end now.
不可能! 上啊!
Never! Come on!
回击!
Fight!
真正的阿尔法... 保护所有的龙
The Alpha... protects them all.
你总是不停带给我惊喜 兄弟
You never cease to amaze me, bud.
谢谢你
Thank you.
没牙仔 你知道这洗不掉的!
Toothless, you know that doesn't wash out!
- 我就知道你会回来的! - 你终于回来了 我的宝贝!
- I knew you'd come back! - You're back, my beauty!
噢! 噢!
Oh! Oh!
暴飞飞!
Stormfly!
噢 过来抱一抱 小暴龙!
Oh, give me a cuddle, Grumpy!
噢!
Oh!
看看我的小公主!
Who's my little princess!
你再也不许离开我了 钩牙
Don't you ever leave again, Hookfang.
就是你 就是你 我好想你...
No, you are. Yes, you are. I missed you...
噢 吐吐... 不是你!
Oh, Barf... Not you!
刚刚御龙那几招真不是吹的
That was some pretty fine dragon-wrangling back there.
你捕龙肯定也是好手 喔!
You'd make a good trapper. Oh!
你也看到了... 碎颅现在需要有人来照看他
You know... Skullcrusher is gonna need somebody to look after him now.
是说我吗?
Me?
荣幸之至
I'd be honored.
你的父亲会和我一样骄傲的
Your father, he'd be every bit as proud as I am.
谢谢 很高兴你在我身边 妈妈
Thank you. I'm really glad you're here, Mom.
我会留在这里的
And here I'll stay.
明白了吧? 我告诉过你要相信这里
See? I told you it was in here.
哈 哈 哈
Ha, ha, ha.
你还是喜欢玩这一招 真是笑死人了
You're still doing that one. That's hilarious.
- 快过来 - 嗯!
- Come here, you. - Mm!
喔!
Ooh!
首领回家了!
The chief has come home!
耶!
Yeah!
首领万岁!
Long live the chief!
首领万岁! 首领万岁!
Long live the chief! Long live the chief!
首领万岁!
Long live the chief!
呀哈哈哈!
Yah-ha-ha-ha!
这里... 就是博克岛
This... is Berk.
虽然有些被破坏 损毁 被冰雪覆盖 但这就是家
A bit trampled and busted and covered in ice, but it's home.
我们的家
It's our home.
那些袭击我们的人残酷 疯狂
Those who attacked us are relentless and crazy.
但那些阻止他们的? 噢... 更是疯狂!
But those who stopped them? Oh... even more so!
我们也许渺小 但是我们所代表的
We may be small in numbers, but we stand for something
却要比世界上任何敌对力量要强大
bigger than anything the world can pit against us.
我们是和平的声音
We are the voice of peace.
慢慢地 我们将改变整个世界
And bit by bit, we will change this world.
喔!
Wow!
现在你看到了 我们有他们没有的东西
You see, we have something they don't.
哦 当然 他们有军队 有舰队
Oh, sure, they have armies, and they have armadas,
但是我们... 我们有...
but we... we have...
我们的龙!
Our dragons!
《驯龙高手2》